<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- 
(Do not remove this comment block.)
Maintained by the GNOME Documentation Project
http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gdp
Template version: 1.0.3
Template last modified: Nov 16, 2000
-->


<!-- =============Document Header ============================= -->

<article id="index"> <!-- please do not change the id -->
	<artheader>
	<title>Tenes Empanadas Graciela Manual</title>
			<copyright>
				<year>2002</year>
				<holder>Quesada, Ricardo</holder>
			</copyright>
		<!-- translators: uncomment this:

		<copyright>
			<year>2000</year>
			<holder>ME-THE-TRANSLATOR (Latin translation)</holder>
		</copyright>

		-->

		<!-- do not put authorname in the header except in copyright - use
		section "authors" below -->

		<!-- Use this legal notice for online documents which depend on -->
		<!-- core GNOME packages.																				-->
		<legalnotice id="legalnotice">
			<para>
				Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
				under the terms of the <ulink type="help" 
					url="gnome-help:fdl"><citetitle>GNU Free Documentation
						License</citetitle></ulink>, Version 1.1 or any later version 
				published by the Free Software Foundation with no Invariant Sections, 
				no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.	A copy of the license
				can be found <ulink type="help" url="gnome-help:fdl">here</ulink>.
			</para>
			<para>
				Many of the names used by companies to distinguish their products and
				services are claimed as trademarks. Where those names appear in any
				GNOME documentation, and those trademarks are made aware to the members
				of the GNOME Documentation Project, the names have been printed in caps
				or initial caps.
			</para>
		</legalnotice>

		<!-- This is the manual version, not application version. --> 
		<releaseinfo>
			This is version 1.0 of the TEG manual.
		</releaseinfo>
	</artheader>
	
	<sect1 id="introduction">
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>Tenes Empandas Graciela (TEG), is a clone of an Argentinian game
		called 'Plan Táctico y Estrátegico de la Guerra', a
		modified clone of the turn based strategy game 'Risk'.
		It is a multi-player game that can be played across the Internet.
		</para>

		<para> The target of the game is to conquer all the countries of
		the world, which are displayed in a map, or to accomplish your secret
		mission (if you prefer to play with secret missions). In order to
		achieve this goal, the player is supposed to create a certain strategy
		(i.e. try to conquer one continent in the first place, protecting its
		borders once this first step have been achieved. Only then, try to conquer
		another continent).</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="crules">
		<title>Playing the game</title>
		<sect2 id="connecting">
			<title>Connecting to the server</title>
			<para>To connect to the server, you must know the address and
				port of the server. The well-known port of the server is 2000.
				You must tell the client this through the <command>connect</command>
				dialog.
			</para>

			<figure>
				<title>Connect dialog</title>
				<screenshot><screeninfo>connect dialog</screeninfo>
					<graphic format="jpg" fileref="figures/connect.jpg" srccredit="riq">
				</graphic></screenshot>
			</figure>

			<para>After filling the 'Connect Dialog', you'll have a new dialog,
				which will ask your favorite color.</para>

			<figure>
				<title>'Select color' dialog</title>
				<screenshot><screeninfo>color dialog</screeninfo>
					<graphic format="jpg" fileref="figures/selectcolor.jpg" srccredit="riq">
				</graphic></screenshot>
			</figure>

			<para>If you select a color that it isn't available, the server will
				select a color for you</para>


		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="starting">
			<title>Starting the game</title>
			<para>In order to start the game, there should be at least 2 and a
				maximum of 6 players connected to the server. Once connected, any
				of the said players can start the game by clicking on the <command>
					start</command> button of his client. No more players are allowed
				when the game has already started</para>
			<para>After clicking on the <command>start</command> button, the `Type of
				Game' dialog will appear.</para>

			<figure>
				<title>Start button</title>
				<screenshot><screeninfo>Start button</screeninfo>
					<graphic format="jpg" fileref="figures/toolbar_start.jpg" srccredit="riq">
				</graphic></screenshot>
			</figure>

			<para>The server, will then distribute all the countries at random
				among the players, providing each country with an army.</para>

			<note>
				<title>Note</title>
				<para>One can also connect to the server as an observer. This enables to follow the
					game, but not to play. It is noteworthy to keep in mind that there is a maximum number of 9
					connections permitted in this mode.</para></note>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 id="armies1">
			<title>Placing the armies for 1st time</title>
			<para> To place the the armies for 1st time, you must wait your turn.
				Once you are given the turn, you must place 5 armies in your countries.
				After that, send them to the server clicking on <command>send armies</command> button.
				Then, you must wait again for your turn, and place another 3 armies in
				your countries. You can place all the armies in one country if you want
				(there is no limit on the number of armies per country). Once all the
				players have placed the 8 armies, you will be able to attack.</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 id="attack">
			<title>Attacking an enemy</title>
			<para>To attack an enemy, you must wait for your turn. When you receive
				the turn you can attack as many times as you want. To attack, you must
				select 2 countries: the source country (your country),
				and the destination country (your opponent country). The source country
				must have at least 2 armies, but there is no restriction on the quantity
				of the destination country. The source and destination countries must be
 			frontier. Frontiers countries are the ones that have common borders or
 			a line that connects them.
			</para>

			<para>When you attack, you throw 'n' dices, where 'n' is the number of
				armies that you have in your country minus one, but no more than 3.
				Your enemy will throw 'm' dices, where 'm' is the number of armies
				that he has in his country, but no more than 3. After that, the results
				of the dices are sorted in a descedig order. </para>

			<para> The results are compared, the greatest result, with the greatest result,
				and so on. If the there is a draw, or if the destination's result is greater,
				then the source country must take one of his armies off, otherwise
				the destination country must take one of his armies off.</para>

 			<para>You will conquer the country if your opponent runs out of armies. In that
				case you can move as much as 3 armies to the conquered country (from the source
				country)</para>

			<para>Armies example:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>If you have 3 armies, and your opponent has 3 armies,
						you will throw 2 dices, and your opponent 3.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>If you have 5 armies, and your opponent has 2 armies,
						you will throw 3 dices, and your opponent 2.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>If you have 1 army, you cant attack</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist> 

			<para>Dices example:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>If you get a: <guilabel>6, 4, 2</guilabel>, and your
						opponent gets <guilabel>6, 3</guilabel>, the result is: <guilabel>
							6 vs. 6</guilabel>,
						and your opponent wins (you take away one of your armies), and
						the other is:<guilabel>4 vs. 3 </guilabel>, and you win (your
						opponent takes away one of his armies).</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para>If you get a: <guilabel>4, 2, 2</guilabel>, and your
						opponent gets <guilabel>3, 2, 1</guilabel>, the result is: <guilabel>
							4 vs. 3</guilabel>, and you wins (your opponent has to take away one
						of his armies). The 2nd result is:<guilabel>2 vs. 2</guilabel>, 
						and your opponent wins (so you have to take away one of your armies),
						and the last result is <guilabel> 2 vs. 1</guilabel> and here you
						win, and your opponent has to take away one of his armies.</para>
				</listitem>

			</itemizedlist> 

			<figure>
				<title>Dices window</title>
				<screenshot><screeninfo>Dices window</screeninfo>
					<graphic format="jpg" fileref="figures/dices.jpg" srccredit="riq">
				</graphic></screenshot>
			</figure>

			<tip>
				<title>Tip</title>
				<para>Don't attack a country that has more armies than yours</para>
			</tip>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 id="attack2">
			<title>After the attack</title>
			<para>After your attack you can <command>Regroup your armies</command>.
				You can move as much as 3 armies from one country to another one (they
 			must be frontier countries), and the army that is moved once, won't be
				able to be moved again in that turn.</para>

			<para> After you finish your <command>Regroup armies</command>, and
				before you <command>End your turn</command> you can <command>Get country card</command>.</para>

			<para>If you want to <command>Get country card</command> you must have
				conquered at least one country in your turn, and if that is OK, you 
				will be given a country card chosen randomly.  If the country that
				represents the card is yours, that country will be
				added 2 armies automatically.  Otherwise you will be allowed to place 2
				armies later if you conquer it. There are 4 types of cards: 
				<command>galleon</command>, <command>cannon</command>, <command>balloon</command>
				or a <command>joker</command>. When you have 3 different cards or 3 cards
				of the same type you can exchange them for armies.</para>

			<informaltable><tgroup cols="2">
					<tbody>
						<row><entry>Number of exchange</entry><entry>Quantity of armies received</entry> </row>
						<row><entry>1</entry><entry>4</entry></row>
						<row><entry>2</entry><entry>7</entry></row>
						<row><entry>3</entry><entry>10 (and now add 5)</entry></row>
						<row><entry>4</entry><entry>15</entry></row>
						<row><entry>5</entry><entry>20</entry></row>
						<row><entry>...</entry><entry>...</entry></row>
			</tbody></tgroup></informaltable>

			<para>After the 3rd exchange, you will have to conquer 2 countries
				(instead of one) to 'get a country card'</para>

			<para>Finally, you must press <command>End turn</command> to finish your turn,
				and give it to the next player</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 id="newturn">
			<title>A new turn</title>
			<para>When all the players finished their turns, a new turn will start. This
				time, the first player to start will be the 2nd player of the last
				turn. This player will have to place a certain amount of armies in his countries.
				If a player has conquered an entire continent, he will have to place:</para>
			<informaltable><tgroup cols="2">
					<tbody>
						<row><entry>Continent</entry><entry>Quantity of armies</entry> </row>
						<row><entry>South America</entry><entry>3</entry></row>
						<row><entry>North America</entry><entry>5</entry></row>
						<row><entry>Africa</entry><entry>3</entry></row>
						<row><entry>Europe</entry><entry>5</entry></row>
						<row><entry>Asia</entry><entry>7</entry></row>
						<row><entry>Oceania</entry><entry>2</entry></row>
			</tbody></tgroup></informaltable>

			<note>
				<title>Note</title>
				<para>Those armies must be placed in the conquered continent</para> 
			</note>

 			<para>After all the players have finished placing their armies, you will be able
				to attack again.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="mission">
		<title>Playing with secret missions</title>
		<para>You can choose between playing with <guilabel>secret mission</guilabel>,
			or to <guilabel>conquer the world</guilabel>.</para>

		<figure>
			<title>Type of game</title>
			<screenshot><screeninfo>Type of game</screeninfo>
				<graphic format="jpg" fileref="figures/toolbar_start.jpg" srccredit="riq">
			</graphic></screenshot>
		</figure>

		<note>
			<title>Note</title>
			<para>If you know that only 2 players are going to play, its better to use
				the 'conquer the world' option</para></note>


		<para>If you play with <guilabel>secret mission</guilabel>, you can win achieving
			your secret mission, or achieving the common `secret' mission,
			which is to conquer 30 countries of the world. If you play with <guilabel>conquer
				the world</guilabel> you win only conquering the entire world.</para>

		<para>The winner is the player who achieves his mission first.</para>

		<para>You can also, change the type of game from the server's console. Just
			type <command>set conquer_world=0</command> or <command>set conquer_world=1</command> to switch
			between <guilabel>secret missions</guilabel> or <guilabel>conquer the world</guilabel>.</para>

		<note>
			<title>Viewing your mission</title>
			<para>To view your secret mission, just click on <guilabel>view->mission</guilabel> in the client</para>
		</note>

		<figure>
			<title>Your mission</title>
			<screenshot><screeninfo>Your mission</screeninfo>
				<graphic format="jpg" fileref="figures/mission.jpg" srccredit="riq">
			</graphic></screenshot>
		</figure>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="server">
		<title>The Server</title>
		<sect2 id="staring">
			<title>Starting the server</title>
			<para>You can start the server, executing the command <command>tegserver</command> or
				from the connect dialog of the client, clicking in the <guilabel>Start server locally</guilabel>
			</para>

			<figure>
				<title>Starting the server locally</title>
				<screenshot><screeninfo>Starting the server locally</screeninfo>
					<graphic format="jpg" fileref="figures/connect.jpg" srccredit="riq">
				</graphic></screenshot>
			</figure>

		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="commands">
			<title>Server commands</title>
 			<para>The server has very useful commands to configure it. Just type <command>help</command> and
				you will see all the available commands.</para>

			<figure>
				<title>Server commands</title>
				<screenshot><screeninfo>Server commands</screeninfo>
					<graphic format="jpg" fileref="figures/server.jpg" srccredit="riq">
				</graphic></screenshot>
			</figure>
		</sect2>

	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="crisk">
		<title>Differences with Risk</title>
		<sect2 id="riskdiff">
			<title>Differences with Risk</title>
			
			<para>I don't know the original Risk rules (I've only played Risk once or twice a looong time ago).
 			So I'm not sure about the differences between both games. If you notice them, please tell me.
			</para>
			<table frame="all"><title>TEG vs. Risk</title>
				<tgroup cols="3">
					<colspec colname="c1">
						<colspec colname="c2">
							<colspec colname="c3">
								<spanspec spanname="hspan" namest="c1" nameend="c3" align="center">
									<thead>
										<row>
											<entry align="center">Topic</entry>
											<entry align="center">TEG</entry>
											<entry align="center">Risk</entry>
										</row>
									</thead>
									<tbody>
										<row>
											<entry>After conquering a country</entry>
											<entry>You can only move at most 3 armies to that country</entry>
											<entry>You can move as many as you want</entry>
										</row>
										<row>
											<entry>After ending your turn</entry>
<entry>You can't place any army, unless you have the card of any
												of your countries,where you can place only 2 armies</entry>
											<entry>You're able to place 3 armies in your countries</entry>
										</row>
										<row>
											<entry>Extra armies for conquering a continent</entry>
											<entry>They MUST be placed inside the continent</entry>
											<entry>They can be placed anywhere</entry>
										</row>
										<row>
											<entry>Placing armies</entry>
											<entry>They are placed at the beginning of each round</entry>
											<entry>You place them before attacking</entry>
										</row>
										<row>
											<entry>Starting a new round</entry>
											<entry>Each round, a different player will start it (round-robin)</entry>
											<entry>Each round, the same player starts it</entry>
										</row>
										<row>
											<entry spanname="hspan">If you notice any other difference, mail it to the list <email>teg-list@lists.sourceforge.net</email>
												Remember that I don't know the Risk rules!
											</entry>
										</row>
									</tbody>
								</spanspec>
							</colspec>
						</colspec>
					</colspec>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="cbugs">
		<title>Bugs</title>
		<sect2 id="bugs">
			<title>Reporting bugs and sending patches to enhance the
				game</title>

			<para>You can contact the author as
				<email>riq@corest.com</email>
				General discussion about this game is carried on the
				<email>teg-list@lists.sourceforge.net</email> mailing list.</para>

		</sect2>
	</sect1>


	<sect1 id="chistory">
		<title>History</title>
		<sect2 id="history">
			<title>Brief history of TEG</title>

			<para>Sebastián Cativa Tolosa, once told me to do this game. I think that
				was in 1996, in a chat we were having in the University. Well, we started
				to think the game. But I don't know why, the project died after 3 or 4 months.
				In 1998, the project was reactivated, but after 2 weeks it died again :(.
				Finally, in February 2000, I started the game again, and it seems that it is
				not dead :-).
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
</article>
